<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="pretty-atom-feed.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <title>Blog Title</title>
  <subtitle>This is a longer description about your blog.</subtitle>
  <link href="https://example.com/feed/feed.xml" rel="self" />
  <link href="https://example.com/" />
  <updated>2025-03-30T00:00:00Z</updated>
  <id>https://example.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name>Your Name</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Welcome to joelegner.github.io Blog</title>
    <link href="https://example.com/blog/2025-03-30/" />
    <updated>2025-03-30T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://example.com/blog/2025-03-30/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Welcome to my blog. I made it on Sunday, March 30, 2025, using the &lt;code&gt;11ty&lt;/code&gt; static website generator. It uses their default theme, because it looks fine and I do not want to worry about formatting. If the desire strikes me later, I might try to change the aesthetics. But for now this will work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;whats-the-point-of-the-blog&quot;&gt;What&#39;s the point of the blog?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I see myself as a curator of good ideas. For now I hope you will accept the tentative definition that &amp;quot;good&amp;quot; means &amp;quot;conducive to achieving of goals in life.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-about-an-example&quot;&gt;How about an example?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;💡Idea: Apply logic to get better results in life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suppose you are engaged in conversation. You want to start off with some groundrules to make the conversation fruitful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You suggest to your interlocutor, &amp;quot;We will be most effective if we try to reason. So, I propose we follow the rules of logic.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;I demand a proof that shows the rules of logic are necessary.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;To demand proof is to assume that reasoning can justify conclusions. But reasoning itself depends on logical principles. Therefore, the act of demanding proof presupposes logic.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Logic seems to be self-evidently valid. As soon as you ask “why” you announce that you will accept reasons. Once you do that you announce you accept reason and logic.  But all logical arguments (including this one) are based ultimately on unprovable assumptions or axioms. They are assumed, not obviously true. C.S. Peirce might add that they are useful in practice, which for him—and you—makes all the difference. Apply logic to get better results in life.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>