<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="pretty-atom-feed.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <title>Blog Title</title>
  <subtitle>This is a longer description about your blog.</subtitle>
  <link href="https://example.com/feed/feed.xml" rel="self" />
  <link href="https://example.com/" />
  <updated>2025-04-03T00:00:00Z</updated>
  <id>https://example.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name>Your Name</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Welcome to joelegner.github.io Blog</title>
    <link href="https://example.com/blog/2025-03-30/" />
    <updated>2025-04-03T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://example.com/blog/2025-03-30/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;situation&quot;&gt;Situation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You have come across a blog that you have not seen before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;complication&quot;&gt;Complication&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You do not know whether to invest any time in reading said blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;question&quot;&gt;Question&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why should I read this blog?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;brief-answer&quot;&gt;Brief Answer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read this blog to learn how to better make progress in your life. Better yet: Read this blog to get smarter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;discussion&quot;&gt;Discussion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do not take credit for the ideas I will show you. I am a humble servent fumbling through life just like you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can I do it? Can I show you how to make better progress? I think so. But it is all credited to other people. My role is currator. I see patterns. And I have seen a lot of snapshots that, when stitched together, create a beautiful and satisfying portrait of something.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some snapshots are filed under Buddhism. Some are filed under Stoicism. Some are filed under philosophy. Some are filed under literature. Some are filed under music.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This blog teaches better thinking. Better thinking helps you make better decisions under uncertainty, achieve more goals, manifest your values, and live life richly. These habits will improve the frequency, quality, and quantity of good times in life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes good decisions move you toward achieving goals. Sometimes they are about improving oneself. When we combine these two: achieving goals and self-improvements, we will call the overall result &lt;em&gt;progress&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes I will treat you like a judge. I will plead my case like a lawyer pleads to a judge. The law has much to say about how to make decisions. It is a microcosm of life and so a fascinating area of study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether you flourish or not depends on action. Action depends on beliefs and conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some actions work to maximize the probability of good outcomes. We will call those workable, helpful, rational, or functional.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some alternative actions work to minimize that probability. We will call those unworkable, unhelpful; irrational, or dysfunctional.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think of all the possible actions you could take in the next, say, five minutes. You could lie down. You could start putting together a puzzle. You could manscape. Among all the possibilities is the one or two you will actual do once we see the movie. The act of taking that action we will call a decision. It cuts off the other actions that could take place at that moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Time and circumstances will cut off even more. And new possibilities will appear. The set of all possible actions is ever changing. It is time dependent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to help you make decisions.
Why? I want you to flourish. I care about you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are all here on this planet without our consent. Not a single one of us consented to being born. We might as well make the best of it. To do that I think means cooperating. Imagine each of us contributing what we know to a global mental world. If we do it right, better things will happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s look at our first theorem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Theorem: Among all possible decisions, some are more likely to lead to human flourishing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suppose you are standing in a puddle of gasoline. You have a lighter in your hand. One decision is to light the lighter. Another is to not light the lighter. Which one is more likely to lead to your flourishing in life?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do you mean by &lt;em&gt;human flourishing&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You understand this already. Think plants. Think puppies. You know when a living thing is fluorishing. But we can give you some more details, too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s look at a hypothetical woman who is flourishing in this world. She knows she deserves not to suffer, because she did not ask to be here. Any time she suffers is a cosmic injustice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She does and says what she believes will make the world a better place. She has good reason to believe it. She engages with all aspects of her humanity. She transcends it too. She continually learns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a new idea fits the bit picture better than an old idea, she makes the replacement. She feels a sense of purpose anchored in reality. She tries to do the right thing. She has compassion for the other passengers on earth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Problems come her way. They cause her concern, but not anxiety. She can handle it. She is cool. She is level headed.  She knows that problems get solved. She knows how to attack some problems already. And when she faces a new problem, she experiments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her tries get better over time, too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another aspect of a flourishing life is a reduction in suffering. Nobody deserves to suffer. Everybody deserves to be freed from suffering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a hypothesis: we can reduce the frequency, quantity, and severity of bad experiences by thinking more clearly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We might say it another way: a good life eliminates unnecessary suffering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am starting a blog on my birthday. This entry prepares the soil for the first blog content entry. That and subsequent entries will follow these rules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The purpose of this blog is to help the reader make progress in life.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Making progress in life includes achieving goals and self-improvement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The blog will be structured like this inaugural entry: situation, complication, question, brief answer, discussion, conclusion, and revision history.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The situation is the staring point.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The complication is the challenge faced.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The brief answer gives the punchline.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The discussion contains analysis, synthesis, and reasoning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The conclusion sums up the entire entry.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you discover an improved purpose, change the purpose.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you change after its published date, document the changes in the Revision History section.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you read this blog before its published date, it is subject to change without a revision history.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If deviating from a rule or blog entry would better serve the purpose of this blog, deviate from the rule.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;revision-history&quot;&gt;Revision History&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will document any edits made after the date of publication.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>